Edwin O. Smith High School Records
© 2006 University of Connecticut
Edwin O. Smith High School Records.
undated, 1956-1968.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center
Edwin O. Smith High School.
39 linear feet.
MSS19980294
In 1955, the Connecticut General Assembly authorized funding for the construction of a junior-senior high school in Mansfield, Connecticut, to be administered by the University of Connecticut. The school opened in the fall of 1958 and remained a division of the UConn School of Education until the summer of 1987.
History
In 1955, the Connecticut General Assembly authorized funding for the construction of a junior-senior high school in Mansfield, Connecticut, to be administered by the University of Connecticut. The $1.2 million allocation was authorized in recognition of the need to training teachers for the schools of Connecticut; to meet the needs for secondary education in the Town of Mansfield resulting from the problem created by the absence of any industrial wealth and by the presence of two large state institutions (UConn and the Mansfield Training School); and to assist the University in attracting and retaining high quality teaching and research staff. Before the school opened the training of teachers of Home Economics and Vocational Agriculture was also added to the charge. The school opened in the fall of 1958 as a division of the School of Education.
The University School was quickly named for Edwin Oscar Smith, acting president of the University (1908) and remained a division of the UConn School of Education until the summer of 1987. On July 1, 1987, the University conveyed the property and buildings of the school to the Town of Mansfield.
Scope and Content
The collection contains documentation of a mid-1960s addition to the school.
Arrangement
Series I: Blueprints ( undated, 1956-1963 )
Series II: Administrative Records and Correspondence ( undated, 1956-1968 )
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Organizations:
University of Connecticut. School of Education.; Edwin O. Smith High School.
Places:
Storrs (Conn.)-- Education.
Subjects:
Education, Secondary--Connecticut--Mansfield.; High schools--Connecticut.; High school teachers--Training of--Connecticut.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Blueprints.; Administrative Records.; Financial Records.
Occupations:
Education.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The Blueprints were donated by Harry Danos, an architect associated with the construction of the building. The provenance of the remaining materials is unknown.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Blueprints, undated, 1956-1963
  - Addition, 1965 (Box Roll)
  - Addition Completion, 1968 (Box Roll)
  - Addition Floor Plan/Finnish Schedule, 1964 (Box Roll)
  - Furniture (room interiors), 1965 (Box Roll)
  - Gymnasium, 1964 (Box Roll)
  - Jr.-Sr. School, 1956 (Box Roll)
  - University High School, 1958 (Box Roll)
  - Vocational Agricultural Center, 1963 (Box Roll)
  - Comprehensives and Preliminaries (Addition), 1963 (Box Roll)
  - Elevation Drawings for Addition (6 pcs.), circa 1963 (Box OS)
  - Artist's Rendering for Auditorium (prelim.), undated (Box OS)
  - Composite Site Studies (3 pcs.), 1963 (Box OS)
  - Poster Presentation with Photos, undated (Box OS)
- Series II: Administrative Records and Correspondence, undated, 1956-1968
  - Bid Specifications, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Rough Sketches, undated (Box 1)
  - Vocational Agriculture Center Correspondence, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Specifications for Vocational Agriculture Center, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Vocational Agriculture Center Transmittals and Correspondence, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Room Study Correspondence, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Science and Art Classroom Plan Studies, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Outline Specifications for Addition, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - General, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Materials Costs Estimates, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Final Design Review (Forms and Correspondence), 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Addition Specifications Document (Clean Copy), 1965 (Box 1)
  - Addition Specifications Document with Signed Contract, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Architect's Inspection Reports, 1965, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Completion of Addition Correspondence, 1965-1968 (Box 2)
  - Requisition for Payment/ Tests, 1965-1966 (Box 2)
  - Inspection Reports, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
  - Change Orders for Addition, 1965-1967 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence Regarding School Plaque, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
  - Completion - Colors and Materials, 1966-1968 (Box 3)
  - Outline Specifications for Completion of Addition (with Mechanical specifications), 1967 (Box 3)
  - Outline Notes for Project Specifications (Completion), 1967 (Box 3)
  - Completion of Addition - Drawings and Plans, 1967-1968 (Box 3)
  - Working Procedure During Construction, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Specifications for Completion of Addition, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Completion - Requisition for Payment, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Completion of Addition Blueprints, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Completion Change Orders, Inspections, and Correspondence, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Doors - Completion, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Public Works Reviews of Final Drawings, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Completion - Shop Drawings (with correspondence) Part I, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Completion - Shop Drawings (with correspondence) Part II, 1968 (Box 3)